Guide to the Peter Kahn papers.
Kahn, Peter papers
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Peter Kahn papers.
14-28-2920
Peter Kahn
3.5 cubic ft.; 82 items.
Correspondence, artwork, lecture notes, photographs, subject files, videotape, audiocassette, broadsides
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Correspondence, artwork, lecture notes, photographs, subject files, and other papers; includes broadsides for events at Cornell and in the Ithaca community; includes videotape and audiocassette of Memorial/Testimonial service, and other printed items including Kahn's artwork.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Professor of Art, Cornell University
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Correspondence, artwork, lecture notes, photographs, subject files, and other papers; includes broadsides for events at Cornell and in the Ithaca community; includes videotape and audiocassette of Memorial/Testimonial service, and other printed items including Kahn's artwork.
Also, "The Unfinished Autobiography of H. Peter Kahn," compiled by Ruth Gannett Kahn and edited by Charlotte Kahn; and spiral bound copies of newspaper articles about Kahn. Typescript on "Religion, Nature and Art," and typescript manuscript of speech, "Technology and Virtue: Joe Blumenthal and the Spiral Press."
Gifts presented to Cornell Library by Peter Kahn on March 20, 1991. Includes medieval manuscripts, caricatures by G. M. Woodward, engravings and other printed teaching samples.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Kahn, Peter.; Woodward, G. M. (George Moutard), 1760-1809
Subjects:
Artists, American; Typography
Form and Genre Terms:
Broadsides.; Photographs.; Engraving; Manuscripts, Medieval
INFORMATION FOR USERS
Access Restrictions:
Contents of Box 7 are restricted to permission of the University Archivist.
Donor retains copyright.
SERIES LIST
Series I: Oversize
Box 1
Series II: Personal
Boxes 2, 3-8
Series III: Correspondence
Box 2
Series IV: Subject Files
Box 2-4
Series V: Course Notebooks, Examples of Work
Box 5
Series VI: Letters, Lines, and Pages
Box 6
Series VII: Letters of reference, Cornell correspondence re: tenure, promotion
Box 7 RESTRICTED
Series VIII: Media
Series IX: Peter Kahn gift to Library
Box 1
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I: Oversize
  - Various posters, broadsides and prints designed by Peter Kahn, Loose (Box 1)
- Series II: Personal
  - Transcript, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Transcript from New York University, curriculum vita
  - Biography (Box 8, Folder 1)
    Excerpts from Peter's Letters to Family, 1952-1976
  - Notes (Box 8, Folder 2)
    Articles and notes
  - Poems (Box 8, Folder 3-4)
    Books of poetry, mostly by students and former students
  - Lauren Hefferon Book (Box 8, Folder 5)
    "Cycle Food", by a former student
  - A Modest Proposal (Box 8, Folder 6)
    Copy of Johnathan Swift's "A Modest Proposal"
  - Books of Poetry (Box 8, Folder 7)
    More poetry from former students
  - The Unfinished Autobiography of H. Peter Khan (Box 8, Folder 8)
    Articles on Peter Khan and his unfinished autobiography
- Series III: Correspondence
  - Correspondence, 1948-1963 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Appointment, publication of articles, sales of artworks, exhibition and lecture arrangements, notes from friends and students, job offers, Bruce Sanderson Award at Williams College
  - Correspondence, 1964-1967 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Exhibitions, notes from friends and students, illustrations, academic matters, proposals, seminars, course outlines
  - Correspondence, 1968-1969 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Notes from friends and students, living arrangements, job offers, war concerns, appointment forms
  - Correspondence, 1968-1969 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    [Not dated - from folder labelled '68-'69] notices of exhibitions, artworks, notes from friends and students, notes re books
  - Correspondence, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Exhibitions, notes from friends and students, academic matters, job offers, lectures, calligraphy work
  - Correspondence, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Notes from friends and students, lectures, appointment letter, job offers, academic matters, books
  - Correspondence, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Lectures, notes from friends and students, congratulations on appointment as professor, books, academic matters
  - Correspondence, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Academic matters, job offers, notes from friends and students, artwork sales, lecture
  - Correspondence, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Notes from friends, academic matters, clippings, job offers, receipt, proposal, clipping
  - Correspondence, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Academic matters, job offers, calligraphy, notes from friends and students, publications, youth activities
  - Correspondence, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Discrimination article and note; letters of referral while P.K. is on leave; job references; notes from friends, students; academic matters; letters of thanks; copies of correspondence re: Messenger Lecture series; letters re: artworks
  - Correspondence, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Notes from friends and students; letters of reference; letters re: artworks; Cornell academic matters; invitations to exhibitions
  - Correspondence, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Notes from friends and students; academic matters; letter of dissatisfaction; invitations to lecture; requests for artworks; letters of reference
  - Correspondence, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Publisher note re: book review; requests for letters of reference; letters of reference; academic matters; invitations to exhibit; notes from friends and students
  - Correspondence, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    Background letter; academic matters; notes from friends and students; exhibition invitation; sales of artworks; award letter
  - Correspondence, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    Academic matters; notes from friends and students; letters of reference; letters re: artworks
  - Correspondence, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    Letters of reference; notes from friends and students; academic matters; funeral bulletin
  - Correspondence, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    Academic matters; request for reference; notes from friends and students; letters re: artworks; letters of reference; retirement announcement and comments; letters re: exhibitions
  - Correspondence, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    Letters from friends and students; requests for letters of reference; letters of reference; academic matters; exhibitions; clipping
  - Correspondence, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    Letters from friends and students; exhibitions; publishers; letters of reference; academic matters; requests for letters of reference
  - Correspondence, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    Letters re: artwork; letters from friends; letters of reference; academic matters
  - Correspondence, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    Letters from friends and students; letters re: artwork, exhibitions, publications; Joni Parrish re: "Focus on Art"; clippings; Brady Foundation; Fosdick-Nelson Gallery, NYS College of Ceramics at Alfred floor plan; poetry
  - Correspondence, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    Letters from friends and students; letters of thanks, exhibition correspondence; clippings; calligraphy; sale of arworks; requests for letter of reference; letter to Governor Cuomo re: Ithaca's west end
  - Correspondence, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    Course plan; letter from NYS Transportation Department; letters from friends and students; exhibitions; sales of artworks; thanks; galleries; Trumansburg matters
  - Correspondence, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    Letters from friends and students; education; exhibitions; clippings; book review; draft of thank you
  - Correspondence, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    Letters of thank you; letters from friends and students; book review and correspondence; letter reacting to Historic Ithaca article; request to speak; letter of support for proposal; lesson plan; vita of Cornell colleague
  - Correspondence, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    Letters from friends and students; resignation from Trumansburg Fire Department; letter of recommendation (draft); gallery re: exhibition
  - Correspondence, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    Letters from friends and students; clippings; exhibitions; thank you letters; model list; artworks; Cornell University events list; wedding announcements
  - Correspondence, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    Letters from friends and students; thank you; receipt from gallery
  - Correspondence, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    Letter in support of public broadcasting; thank you from Warren Benson; letters from friends and students; thank you letters
  - Correspondence, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    Letter to "Change N.Y."; letter from Arnold Singer; note from Alice Irwin
  - Correspondence, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    Thank you from City Club of Ithaca
  - Correspondence (Box 2, Folder 34)
    Notes from friends and students
  - Cornell correspondence, 1960-1965 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    Memos, proposal, lesson plan
  - Cornell correspondence, 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    Letters of recruitment, memos, thank you notes, clipping, receipt, correspondence with Felix Reichmann concerning a printing machine
  - Cornell correspondence, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    Thank you notes, memos, letters of reference, campus events, resignation from committee, agreement to serve on a committee, support for lecture, financial aid information
  - Cornell correspondence, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    Memos, thank you letters, financial aid inquiry, Cornell Cinema, Empire State Youth Theatre Institute
  - Cornell correspondence, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    Memos, lecturer recruitment, Alumni News, thank you note, comments on Senate
  - Cornell correspondence, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    Syllabus, memos, thank you note, letters re: Campus Store
  - Cornell correspondence, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    Memos, thank you notes
  - Cornell correspondence, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Cornell correspondence, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    Thank you notes, book reviews, "Future of the Department"
  - Cornell correspondence, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    Memos, Performing Arts Center, thank you note, student funding
  - Cornell correspondence, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    Book review, CAU, memos, memorial service bulletin for George Winter, library book reserve list
  - Cornell correspondence, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    Book review, CAU memo of resignation, memos, retirement letter, payment for artwork, notes of thanks, letter from friend
  - Cornell correspondence, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    Permission memo and form, memo re: Zeus, letter of appointment to Professor Emeritus, thank you notes, Alumni News
  - Cornell correspondence, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    "Noye's Fludde" program, memo re: continuing on Admissions Committee, thank you note
  - Cornell correspondence, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    List of gift books, memos of thanks, memos, copy of article, "Art on Campus at Cornell University," note re: Felix Reichmann memorial statement, memorial service bulletin for Felix Reichmann
  - Cornell correspondence, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 50)
    Note and proposal, memos re: Felix Reichmann memorial statement and copy of draft, memorial service bulletin for J. Saunders Redding, memos re: James Hutton book
  - Cornell correspondence, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 51)
    Memos re: James Hutton book, memorial service bulletin for Eric Blackall, notes of thanks, campus mailing, lesson plans, CAU evaluations
  - Cornell correspondence, 1991-1992 (Box 2, Folder 52)
    University Lectures Committee memo, thank you notes, gift book list, memos
  - Cornell correspondence, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 53)
    Notes of thanks, news release from Johnson Museum, Vicious Circle, letter re: type, presses, etc. in Risley Print Shop, correspondence re: Gannett book donation
- Series IV: Subject Files
  - A Little Writing Book, Peter Kahn, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - A Song To David, Christopher Smart, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 72)
    Facsimile, cover by Peter Kahn
  - Advanced Placement, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 54)
    Correspondence, course outlines, conference materials
  - Advanced Placement, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Advanced Placement, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 56-57)
  - Art and Math, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 58-59)
    Proposed course outline, bibliographies, course outline
  - Art Education, 1964-1973 (Box 2, Folder 60)
    Memos, committee lists, articles
  - Articles, 1968-1984 (Box 2, Folder 61)
    Articles about H. Peter Kahn
  - Bibliography (and other imponderables), 1964, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 62)
    Notes, drafts
  - Book and Bowl, 1990-1994 (Box 2, Folder 63)
    Memos
  - Book covers, Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Cards and pamphlets designed by Peter Kahn (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - CAU, 1978-1989 (Box 2, Folder 64)
    Course outline, memos
  - CAU Drawings, 1991-1994 (Box 2, Folder 65)
    Course lists, memos
  - Centaur Press, 1966-1977 (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Chautauqua, 1980-1984 (Box 2, Folder 67)
    Memos, course catalogs
  - Colleagues, Friends, CommitteeWork, 1954-1974 (Box 2, Folder 68)
    Memos, catalogs
  - Cornell Libraries art, Undated (Box 2, Folder 74)
  - David Starr Jordan Prize, 1978-1990 (Box 2, Folder 69)
    Clippings, articles, catalogs
  - E. B. White, Undated (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - Educational Services, 1964-1991 (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - Good Paper (Box 3, Folder 1-3)
    Samples of paper
  - Granville, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Hamburg and Other Matters, 1989-1991 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Reports, memos, catalogs
  - Hamburg (Budges and Cornell Abroad), 1989-1993 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Correspondence, paper, writings in German, reports, drafts, clippings
  - Hamburg II, 1986-1991 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    Correspondence, reports, drafts
  - Historic Ithaca, 1975-1979 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    Documentation, by-laws, proposals, petition
  - Historic Ithaca, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    Drawing, front cover and contents of "H. I." binder, minutes of meetings, reports, newsletters
  - Historic Ithaca, 1982-1983 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    Mission statement, minutes of meetings, form letters, newsletters
  - Historic Ithaca, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    Minutes of meetings, newsletters, report, form letter, draft
  - Historic Ithaca, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    "Steering Nonprofits," drafts
  - Introductory (#2 Introduction), n.d. (Box 3, Folder 13)
    Drafts and notes for book
  - Lectures, Course Outlines, 1961-1990 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    Course outlines, lesson plans, drafts, resources
  - Lectures, Outlines: CAU, 1970-1993 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    Correspondence, CAU announcements, draft, mailing
  - Leonardo, 1980-1981 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    Correspondence, drafts, one reprint
  - Matters Graphic, 1958-1966 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    Catalogs, reprints and booklets re: types, papers, ink, pens, bookbinding, art and drafting supplies (many undated)
  - News Clips (NY, LSU, Hampton), 1946-1968 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    Newspaper and magazine clippings
  - Peter Kahn et al, Photographs, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 19-20)
    People, events, artworks (prints [some matted] and negatives)
  - PK Publicity Newspapers (CU + Victoria, BC), 1959-1994 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    Clippings, magazine articles
  - Photo Publicity, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 22)
    Prints and negatives of artworks
  - Preservation, 1982-1983 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    Clippings and reports (Historic Ithaca)
  - Presses, Correspondence (Graphics-Materials-Ideas), 1960-1966 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    Catalogs, proposal, memo
  - Presses, etc., 1969-1988 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    Letters, list, catalog and updates
  - Rose Goldsen Committee, 1992-1994 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    Proposals and cover letters
  - Summer Ithaca, 1961-1976 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    Booklets
  - Theatre Book, 1988-1989 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    Correspondence, copies, drafts, agreement
  - Tompkins County Arts Council, 1981-1985 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    Form letters, minutes of meetings
  - Type Classification, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 30)
    Notes
  - Typology, 1965-1988 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    Catalogs, copies,
  - University Affairs Victoria, 1969-1971 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    Correspondence, clippings
  - Wells College mostly Hammer Press, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    Correspondence, reports, catalogs, drafts
  - "Decorated folders", n.d. (Box 3, Folder 34)
    4 manila folders with sketches or calligraphy on them
  - Publications, 1946-1965 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Exhibitions, resource materials, small books
  - Publications, 1967-1978 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    Exhibitions, post cards, small books
  - Publications, 1982-1989 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Publications, 1991-1993 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    Exhibitions, small books, postcards
  - Publications, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 5)
    Exhibitions, postcards, stationery, catalog
  - Publications (magazines and journals), 1970-1976 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    Karate, Linguistic Inquiry, The Metropolitan Museum of Art Bulletin
  - Reprints by others, 1956-1980 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    Biasin-Gesca
  - Reprints by others, 1967-1985 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    Harrington-Koselleck
  - Reprints by others, 1963-1982 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    Lucas-Whyte
- Series V: Course Notebooks, Examples of Work
  - Sketchbook, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Outlines/drawing courses/graphic communication
  - Notebook, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    Course for 6 yr Ph.D. the Sources of Modernism
  - Notebook, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    Weimar course
  - Notebook, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 3)
    Theatre course
  - Notebook/Sketchbook, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 4)
    Pictorial Means Modernist Lessons
  - Wooden Press, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    Sketches and notes
  - Examples of Work, 1967-1998 (Box 5)
    Posters, concert programs
- Series VI: Letters, Lines, & Pages
  - Proofs, ca.1982 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Proofs, ca.1982 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Printed copy, ca.1982 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    Final unsewn copy and bound copy (typing paper box)
  - Printed copies, ca.1982 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    2 copies, unsewn (practice?)
  - Illustrations and examples, ca.1982 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    Photocopies
  - Chapter on tools, ca.1982 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    Printed samples, notes, typed mss., photocopies
  - Book II, ca.1982 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    Section on constructed letters and types, notes
  - Roman letters: square, rustic, uncial, ca.1982 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Medieval Hands, ca.1982 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    Notes, illustrations
  - Italic Folio (Renaissance hands), ca.1982 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    Notes,
  - III Composing the Page, ca.1982 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Letter geneology [sic], ca.1982 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    Notes and examples
  - Carolingian Foundation Folio, ca.1982 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Front Matter, ca.1982 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    Original copy Letters Lines Pages
  - Front Matter, ca.1982 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    Correspondence about book, publisher's letters, grant support, etc.
  - Front Matter, ca.1982 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    Drafts, typed text, notes, examples
- Series VII. Letters of reference, Cornell correspondence re: tenure, promotion RESTRICTED
  - Correspondence, 1958-1970 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1971-1974 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1975-1979 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1980-1983 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1984-1986 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1987-1990 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1991-1996 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Series VIII. Media
  - Kahn, H Peter: Video of Memorial, Anabel Taylor, CU, Feb 22, 1997; V-373
- Series IX: Peter Kahn gift to Library
  - "The Windmill", by David Cox, engraved by E. P. Brainard, 1886 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Mezzotint
  - "L'incendie", A. Legros, Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Pages 55-56 (Genesis 26-27) from Bruce Rogers (?) Bible (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Folio li of a 15th century printed book including the lives of John the Evangelist and Thomas the Apostle, Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Folio cccxxxi from the Cologne Chronicle, included with facsimile pages and introductory text, Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Engraved plate from octavo book (?) incorporating words "Soyez parfait comme votre Pere celeste est parfait" and numbered III. Page 143, ca. 1800 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Color lithograph of Æchmea fulgens, Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Leaf from Le Charivari with lighograph (numbered 118) by Daumier, Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Print of caricature by G. M. Woodward title "The Glorious Revolution of the World", Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Print of caricature by G. M. Woodward title "Drops of Comfort and Draughts of Delight", Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Cover of The Colophon with pictorial design by R. Kent (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Folio ccv from the Nuremberg Chronicle, Undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Printed leaf from folio book with text beginning "Fredegonde et Brunehaut" and lithograph by Rouault, Undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Chromolithograph of orchid Phalaenopsis casta, Undated (Box 1, Folder 6)